<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some particulars concerning the law, sent to Oliver Cromwell, who is chief ruler in these nations, according to man: and to the counsellors, who sit in counsel with him: wherein is plainly laid down the difference betwixt the righteous law of God, and those laws which are made and acted in the will of man; and how they who make and act those laws, which are according to the will of man, and contrary to the law of God, are found opposing the righteous law of God, and so are transgressors of that law which is according to that in the conscience. With a vvord of discovery of the cruel oppression of the priests, who call themselves ministers of Christ and the Gospel, which gives freedom; but they are found to be opposers, and out of the life that gave forth the scriptures, and so with it judged, which is according to the law of God, which gives freedom to the righteous seed, but have cleared themselves from Christ, who disobey his doctrine, and sue men at the law, and take treble damages, contrary to the scriptures. With a word of exhortation to the rulers and magistrates, to own the righteous law of God, which will cut down sin, and cleanse the land of evil doers, and discover the deceivers of the people.</title>
            <author>Camm, John, 1604?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E740_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866094</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79527)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 114:E740[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some particulars concerning the law, sent to Oliver Cromwell, who is chief ruler in these nations, according to man: and to the counsellors, who sit in counsel with him: wherein is plainly laid down the difference betwixt the righteous law of God, and those laws which are made and acted in the will of man; and how they who make and act those laws, which are according to the will of man, and contrary to the law of God, are found opposing the righteous law of God, and so are transgressors of that law which is according to that in the conscience. With a vvord of discovery of the cruel oppression of the priests, who call themselves ministers of Christ and the Gospel, which gives freedom; but they are found to be opposers, and out of the life that gave forth the scriptures, and so with it judged, which is according to the law of God, which gives freedom to the righteous seed, but have cleared themselves from Christ, who disobey his doctrine, and sue men at the law, and take treble damages, contrary to the scriptures. With a word of exhortation to the rulers and magistrates, to own the righteous law of God, which will cut down sin, and cleanse the land of evil doers, and discover the deceivers of the people.</title>
                  <author>Camm, John, 1604?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed, Anno Dom. 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Camm.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 9".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Some Particulars Concerning the Law, SENT TO Oliver Cromwell, Who is chief Ruler in theſe Nations, according to man: And to the Counſellors, who ſit in Counſel with him: wherein is plainly laid down the difference betwixt the righteous Law of God, and thoſe Laws which are made and acted in the will of man; and how they who make and act thoſe Laws, which are according to the Will of man, and contrary to the Law of God, are found oppoſing the righteous Law of God, and ſo are tranſgreſſors of that Law which is according to that in the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>With a vvord of diſcovery of the cruel oppreſſion of the Prieſts, who call themſelves Miniſters of Chriſt and the Goſpel, which gives freedom; but they are found to be Oppoſers, and out of the life that gave forth the Scriptures, and ſo with it judged, which is according to the Law of God, which gives freedom to the righteous ſeed, but have cleared themſelves from Chriſt, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey his Doctrine, and ſue men at the Law, and take treble da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, contrary to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>With a word of Exhortation to the Rulers and Magiſtrates, to own the righteous Law of God, which will cut down ſin, and cleanſe the Land of evil doers, and diſcover the Deceivers of the People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118355:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Riend, thou ſaieſt, That in thy conſcience tells thee, that there is no Law that is extant by which the people of God are kept in bondage; to thee I did alledge the Act of <hi>Mary,</hi> which I ſay is contrary to that in the Conſcience, which is of God, for her Law did cauſe the righteous to ſuffer, which guarded the Jeſuites, which guard the Prieſts now; which thou with it wouldſt limit the holy one, and caſt the Saints into holes, and priſons, and dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, and counteſt it juſt; and ſome are beat and ſtockt, and cruelly perſecuted, and then after ſent to Priſon; ſee if thy Law here do keep Peace, or break it, and give liberty to all the peace breakers and fighters, and ſtrikers, for them to beat, to ſtock, and after ſend them to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and there the wicked, the fighters, and ſtrikers rejoyce over them, and they can ſcarce walk in the ſtreets; and this Law thou counteſt juſt, which priſons the righteous, and encourages the evil doers, which is contrary to the Law of God, which is according to that in the Conſcience, and which is contrary to <hi>Paul</hi> the Miniſter of Chriſt, who ſaid, if any thing be revealed to him that ſtands by, let the firſt hold his peace; and if <hi>Paul</hi> were here again to go up and down the Synagogues, and diſpute with them, to bring them off the figures and ſhadows, to bring them up to the ſubſtance. Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Act would take hold of him; and he was made manifeſt to the Conſciences of all; and here thy Act is contrary to that in the Conſcience, which would limit the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And thy Act, as Queen <hi>Maries,</hi> would take hold upon <hi>Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets, and Chriſt, who was ſuppoſed to be the Carpenters ſon, who went up and down in the Synagogues, and was hated of the Prieſts, and when he ſpoke in the Synagogues, they were full of fury; and there again thy Law is contrary to that of God in the conſcience, and except thou doeſt repent, God will remove thy Kingdom: and if thy Laws were upon them that act, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that in the conſcience, fighters, envious, quarrellers, drunkards, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, and all unrighteous, ſuch Law; we own, this is wholſom and good, but that which would limit the holy One, and the Juſt, we cannot own.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is another Law which is acted contray to that in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to put men to death for Cattle or money, when they were (according to the Law of God) to make reſtitution, if not, they were to be ſold for their Theft, and there they had ſpace to repent, for that in the conſcience will let them ſee what they have done.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and another thing is acted in the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion, contrary to the light of Chriſt in the conſcience; men that cannot ſwear, but abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt, who ſaith, ſwear not at all, for what is more then yea and nay, is evil; and the Apoſtle ſaid, My Brethren ſwear not at all, leſt you fall into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118355:2"/>and ſome that cannot ſwear, ſuch are fined and priſoned, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuffer now, becauſe they cannot ſwear; and ſo you would bring them into condemnation, and into the evil contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt</p>
            <p>Fourthly, another Law is acted contrary to that of God in the conſcience, that men are forced to pay Prieſts tithes, and ſo deny Chriſt come in the fleſh; and if they will not pay Prieſts tithes, they ſue them at the Law, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon them, and that Law requires treble damages, and this Law is oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contrary to that of God in the Conſcience, neither is there honeſty in it; I charge it upon you, for <hi>Moſes,</hi> which had the Law, and gave it forth to the Prieſts and people, and the Prieſts that ſhould receive Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes, they were to have a Store-houſe to put it in, and it was to be filled with Tithes, but it is not ſo with you; and all the ſtrangers and the widdows, and the Fatherleſs were to come to be filled within the Prieſts Gates: and this the Prieſt was to Miniſter out of the Store-houſe; a figure of the everlaſting Prieſt, who Miniſters out of the everlaſting treaſury: the Apoſtle who preached him, ſaid, the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that received Tithes was changed, and the Law was changed alſo; and yet you have a Law, that if any one do not pay the Prieſts Tithes he muſt pay treble damages, or lye in Goal, as many lye in Goal now, becauſe they cannot deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, pay the Prieſts Tithes; but they witneſs him, and deny the changable Prieſthood, which you give Tithes to, but no Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe; who deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, though you talk of him in words, but no Store-houſe to fill all the widdows, the fatherleſs, and ſtrangers in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that there might be no beggar in <hi>England,</hi> as there was no beggar to be in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but be fed within the Prieſts Gates which receive Tithes: But by this Law, by which your Prieſts receive Tithes, you help the Prieſts to make many beggars, which is contrary to the Scriptures, and that of God in the conſcience both, and by that Law many righteous ones ſuffer; all who own Chriſt in life, ſuffer by your Low, and are oppreſt; and all your Laws acted contrary to that of God in the Conſcience: that of God in the Conſcience will teſtifie and witneſs againſt you, and your Laws, and witneſs the Law of God, which is according to that in the Conſcience, which is perfect, and endures for ever.</p>
            <p>You that ſwear, deny the Lord Jeſus Chriſt that bought you, and his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and you that compel men to give Tiches, and you that take them are men that deny the Lord Jeſus Chriſt come in the fleſh, the ſubſtance; you that ſue men at the Law, deny the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for he ſaith, in all your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, let your yea, be yea, and your nay be nay.</p>
            <p>And if you had a Law given forth to keep peace upon them that act contrary to the light of Chriſt in their conſcience, and put in juſt mens hands, to be executed; but ſuch are turned forth that are faithful, that are juſt, and ſo here you encourage evil doers, fighters, quarrellers, and drunkards, that they that fear the Lord, can ſcarce paſs; to that in all your Conſciences I ſpeak, that with it you may ſee your ſelves, and what is acted in the Nation.</p>
            <p>There is another thing in the Nation, acted by them in Authority, which is contrary to that of God in the Conſcience; with ſuch many have been fined and impriſoned, becauſe they could not reſpect perſons, for if they did, they were convinced by that in the Conſcience, to be tranſgreſſors of the righteous Law of God; and their Judges, Juſtices, and Maiors would force them to ſin againſt, and contrary to that of God in the Conſcience, in bowing to them
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118355:3"/>with hat, and reſpect the perſon, which that in the Conſcience, which is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the righteous Law of God, ſaith, Thou ſhalt not bow down to any, nor worſhip any but God; and he that reſpects perſons and would have others to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect perſons, is convinced by that in the conſcience, to be a tranſgreſſor of the righteous Law of God; to that of God in all your conſciences I ſpeak, which lets you ſee you ſhould not do ſo, and yet you do ſo, and would have others to do ſo; and them that do not, ye perſecute, priſon or fine with great ſummes of money; to the light of Chriſt in all your conſciences I ſpeak, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all you that act contrary to it, and witneſs me eternally; to that in the conſcience I ſpeak which reſpects no mans perſon: He that receives the Law from God, dwells in the Light of God, and he doth not reſpect any mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor the Law which is received from God: and he that doth reſpect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, this Law goes upon him, and that in his conſcence, which is according to this Law of God, doth convince him to be a tranſgreſſor of this Law.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Prieſts ſhould have Store-houſes, that the Fatherleſs chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and widdows might thither come and be refreſhed, that there might be no beggars in <hi>England,</hi> as there was to be no beggar in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but the Prieſts and their Agents in raking terble damages, by vertue of your Law, have made both widdows and Fatherleſs to beg by reaſon of their cruel oppreſſion, for they took of one widdow in lieu of her Tithes 11 s. 4 d. when all her whole eſtate, after her debts were paid, would not yield to ſo much, and ſo left widdow and fatherleſs both to beg or ſtarve; and this is their charity to the poor; and many more in <hi>Weſtmerland, Lancaſhire,</hi> and <hi>Cumberland,</hi> who ſtand in obedience to the righteous Law, made manifeſt, and witneſs the ſubſtance, and deny the types, and ſo cannot put into the Prieſts mouths they make them pay, ſomedouble damages, and ſome treble damages, to the making many poor; for they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity are a prey to this Generation; For the Law that is made by the Will of man, is made a ſnare, and a trap to take hold of them who ſtand in obedience to the righteous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw of God, which is according to that of God in the conſcience, and this other is contrary to the Law of God in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>And this was I moved to write to the Heads and Rulers of the Nations, who ſit in Counſel together, to exhort and charge them to ſtand in the Counſel of God, and to mind the righteous Law of God, which is according to that in the conſcience, and that this Law of yours may be put in Execution, to be executed by righteous men, who reſpect no mans perſon, and then it will take hold upon the tranſgreſſors: and they who live up in obedience to this Law of God, which is pure, which endures for ever, will own and witneſs you and your Law, if you be obedient to this Law of God which is pure, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of God in every mans conſcience, for his Lavv is not made for the righteous, but for the tranſgreſſor: and if theſe be owned by you in your lives, you will put it in execution and it will take hold upon all lyars, ſwearers, drunkards, whore mongers, diſſemblers, cheaters, hypocrites, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of thoſe who obey this righteous Law of God; and it will take hold upon all fighters, quarrellers, and vain-Contenders, and upon all falſe teachers, who pretend themſelves Miniſters of Chriſt, but abide not in the Doctrine of Chirſt, which reſpect mens perſons, but are Antichriſts, and deny the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118355:3"/>in their lives, but take them to trade withal, and ſo deceive the people, telling them they are gifted, and ſell them a Carnal letter, and ſo kill them, for the letter killeth, and ſo devour ſouls for diſhoneſt gain: the Lord hath a controverſie with them, hold them not up; for if you partake with them in their ſin, you will partake with them in their plagues, for their fruits make them manifeſt; for if any in obedience to this righteous Law, put not into their mouthes, they prepare war againſt them, and ſue them at Law, or Agents for them, and take treble damages, as many can witneſs in theſe four Northern-Counties; and ſo they oppreſs the righteous, and none reſiſteth them; and now it is come to you who are over the Nations, and it ſtands at your door, and if you ſuffer thoſe things to be, and count it juſt, I will viſit you for theſe things, ſaith the Lord: For I bear teſtimony againſt them, and my witneſs is true, that they are cruel oppreſſors, greedy devourers, Caterpillars, who have done no good at all, but kept the people in blindneſs and ignorance, making them light and vain, ſtrengthning their hands in in iquity, and ſhut the Kingdom of heaven againſt men, that if any would return from their evil waies, they pull them back: all the Scriptures witneſs againſt them, if you will own Scriptures, and that in your Conſcience witneſſeth againſt them; for you had experience of them; and if you hold up that which is contrary to your conſcience, God is greater, and will condemn you, and cut you down; were not your Promiſes and Covenants to take oppreſſion from off the people of God? have you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the dayes of your calamity and hardſhip, when you vowed unto the Lord? and prayed unto him and he hath preſerved you? and were not all your pretences to take off oppreſſion? and now the power is in your hand, and the Lord hath left you without excuſe; for now you have time to pay your vows unto the Lord, and to take off oppreſſion, and to take away all thoſe Laws which are contrary to the Law of God, which is pure; and if ye will not own the Lord in his own work, he will do it another way, and you ſhall be caſt by, as not worthy, with the reſt that were caſt out before you, who were not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: and therefore if you will own the righteous Law of God, which is pure, he will own you, and preſerve you; but if you uphold thoſe Laws which are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of man, and contrary to the will of God, you ſhall be as duſt before the wind, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it. And thus I have cleared my conſcience unto you, and that of God in your conſciences ſhall eternally witneſs me to be a lover of your ſouls, and of the righteous ſeed of God, a well-wiſher of the Peace of <hi>Sion,</hi> called by the world,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Camm.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <p>I Will ariſe now, ſaith the Lord, and threſh, and ſcatter, and beat to pieces; now will I ariſe ſaith the Lord, and all bonds muſt be broken aſunder, which are made with the earthly will, and all Churches gathered with the earthly will, with the earthly letter, who hath not the life, will be ſcattered and broken aſunder, that the pure it ſelf may ariſe which is bound with thoſe bonds, which the carnal mind makes Laws and Acts; but now will I ariſe ſaith the Lord, who is the King, the Law-giver, and all who have not received the Law from him, but make Laws with their inventions, muſt fall, and all their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel come to nothing in the end; though they may ſtand, and have their time
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118355:4"/>a while; and therefore to that in every one of your Conſciences I ſpeak, which is the light of Chriſt, in it wait, to guide your minds to God, and it is but one, and it will call you out of your reaſonings, and turn your minds towards God, and deny all that which doth protect and preſerve that which is not of God, and condemn it: and where God is made manifeſt to raign, for that doth protect the juſt, and is a terrour to the unjuſt, in your ſelves and without, ſo wait all in your meaſure on the light of God within, to guide your minds to God, that ye may grow as plants to receive the living water, to nouriſh you to eternal life, to that which is pure in every one of you do I ſpeak, which ſhall witneſs me, and condemn all you that hate it: which if you take heed to it, it will call your minds out of the world, to forſake the luſts and pleaſures of it, and turn your minds towards God, and let you ſee that God is near and preſent, who is terrible and dreadful to the wicked; in him the righteous rejoyce and are glad, ſo wait all for Counſel from God, and God Almighty direct your minds; for all your Laws which have been made and acted in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from the light, and contrary to it, and the Law of God, which is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the light of Chriſt in your conſciences, all thoſe Laws that have been acted from it, and contrary to the light of Chriſt, have been murder with the murderous nature; and with the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every one that comes into the world withal, vvith this light they are all to be condemned, and with the perfect Law of God to be judged, which is according to the light of Chriſt in the Conſcience, which light of Chriſt owns the Law of God, and which Law of God owns the light of Chriſt in every mans conſcience; and the light of Chriſt in every mans conſcience which is perfect, witneſſeth the Law of God to be perfect, and witneſſeth againſt all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aws which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Light of Chriſt in every mans conſcience, and which is contrary to the Law of God, which is according to that in the Conſcience: So to the light of Chriſt in all your conſciences I do ſpeak, that you with it may wait upon God, to receive your Laws from God, which is perfect, and endures for ever; elſe your Laws which you make in your own wills, which is not perfect and doth not endure for ever; which the Law of God doth, and that in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: so with the light of Chriſt, all ſuch Laws, Law-givers, and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, are to be condemned with the light of Chriſt, which doth endure for ever: and the Law of God which is perfect and doth endure for ever, all ſuch are judged with it, which are contrary to it: So this is the word of God to you, and a warning to you all.</p>
            <p>They that be in the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, do not reſpect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; they that be out of the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, do reſpect perſons, though they may profeſs him, and then the life makes the difference: as it is manifeſt now in <hi>England,</hi> who be in the Faith, who be out of the Faith: and they that be in the perfect law of God, according to the light of Chriſt, in the conſcience, do not reſpect perſons: for he that doth reſpect perſons, is convinced by the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, to be a tranſgreſſor of the law of God; ſo that they that do reſpect perſons, do walk contrary to that in the conſcience, and the law of God, and are convinced by the light of Chriſt in the conſcience, and to be tranſgreſſors; and this is for all the powers on earth; take warning, that with the light of Chriſt you may ſee what you act, and what you acted from, contrary to this light: you are to be condemned by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118355:4"/>it: all ye that reſpect perſons, walk contrary to the Law of God, contrary to the Faith: There is the difference, the one lives in the light of Chriſt, which witneſſeth the Law of God, which is perfect, and the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which none of theſe that do live here doth reſpect perſons: now all thoſe that do profeſs the Law of God, and Faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect perſons, are out of it, and here it is the life that makes the difference, and in it is the Unity.</p>
            <p>TO the Heads and General of this Land, to ſtand in the Counſel of God that you may be directed by his wiſdom which orders all things, for by it all things were made, and if you make a Law with your own wills, over that in the conſciences of men, that God will throw down, you and your Laws: For that which exerciſeth the conſcience, is the pure light of God, which leads up to God, out of all filthineſs, and uncleanneſs, and corruption, which the Law of God takes hold upon; he or them that act contrary to a pure conſcience: Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, and the powers that be, are ordained of God, for conſcience ſake; now if a Law be made over the conſcience that is pure, that Law is againſt God, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for keeping their conſcience clean, did ſuffer death; as God hath given to every one a light, and a meaſure to profit withal, minde every one that which is of God in you, to teach you to walk to God before him; and as it teacheth you, and enlightens your underſtandings, it will teach how to direct others, and ſo to judge of things eternal, ſo far as that is born up in your underſtandings, which is eternal; and as every one hath a meaſure, ſo every one to improve his talent, and not limit God to learned men, as hath long been, which have learned but their natural languages, ſo their original grounds is external, their word and light is external, and their preaching and gift is an external gift, and they go to you Magiſtrates who hath an external Law, to uphold them in their external Miniſtry, for your Law doth alter and change, which is external; now that which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, with it to judge things eternal, that cannot be but to limit God; for he that hath the firſt gift of God, hath that which is perfect, and that which is perfect is eternal, &amp; ſuch have a deſcerning to know the gift of God, from the gift of man; and who are ſent to preach the everlaſting Goſpel, hath that which is eternal, that which is everlaſting hath no end; and he that judgeth of theſe things is eternal, that can diſcern the everlaſting Goſpel from words; and the promiſe was, that the ſeed of the woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head; now thou that canſt witneſs the head of the Serpent bruiſed in thee, and the ſeed of the woman heads in thee, which is Chriſt, witneſſeth the Promiſes of God fulfilled in thee, which is the glad tidings to the ſoul, and the ſoul come out of death; and here is Chriſt Jeſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed within, and this miniſtry is not man not by man, but by the Will of God, which the will of man knows not; For the natural man knows not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118355:5"/>the things of God; now every man in his firſt birth and ſtate may ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be natural, and is not able to judge of the things of God, which be eternal; the ſpiritual man judgeth all things, yea the deep things of God; but this is the ſecond man: therefore all friends take heed of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with evil thoughts, that minde that reſpecteth perſons, Judgeth with evil thoughts, and it is the Carnal part within, who is not of the Faith: but who i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, is without reſpect of perſons; and therefore as God hath given you a meaſure of a light within, let that guide your minds, and keep you in the fear of the Lord, and if you love that light and walk in it, there is no occaſion of ſtumbling; and if you hate that light, then you ſtumble at noon-day, and there is your condemnation: loving this light, and bringing your works to this light; ſo far as this light hath Judged you in particular, ſo far you may judge in general; for that Judge is but one, and waiting in that light which keeps you in the fear of the Lord, waiting upon the Lord, to be made partakers of the precious Faith, for the myſterie of Faith is held in a pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and walking in this light, it enlightens your conſciences, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, walking in it you have union one with another, for the light is but one, which will diſcover all imagined lights, falſe worſhips, wayes and Churches, and draw you up to the Church in God, the fountain of light; and their Faith is but one, which purifieth the heart, which ſtands in God, which is a myſterie held in a pure Conſcience, and all who are in it are one, if they be ten thouſand. God Almighty bleſs, direct and keep all you that fear him, how to wait upon and walk before him, and be low, and ſtand in the Counſel of God, that whatſoever you do may proſper: But if you go out of the Counſel of God, pride, high-mindedneſs and oppreſſion, and grinding the faces of the poor gets up; now your minds being guided by that which is pure, it is croſs to the carnal, which oppreſſeth the poor in particular, if it be not croſt; and out of it ariſeth pride, if the pure Spirit of the Lord be not your guide and head; and if there be no oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion within, then there is none without; for wo is unto him that is covered, but not with the Spirit of the Lord—Therefore minde every one what you are covered withal.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118355:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
